Hello.
In the previous videos, we talked about the
properties of numbers, which are properties 1 to 12.
And we agreed that any dealing we have with numbers
must happen within the framework of these 12 properties.
In this video, or at the end of this video, God willing,
we will start to discover that these 12 properties have shortcomings.
There are some situations and some things related to numbers
that these properties fail to explain.
And we must find another way
to deal with these situations.
Okay, until the last video, we were talking about
numbers in a somewhat loose way, meaning we weren't
very precise about the type of numbers we were discussing.
In this video, God willing, or specifically from the beginning
of this video, God willing, we need to be a bit careful in our dealings with numbers.
Meaning, when we talk about numbers, we need to know
which type of numbers we are talking about.
Why? We'll see in a bit.
The first type we have of numbers is what we call
the Natural Numbers, and we denote it with the heavy N, like this.
We call them the Natural Numbers.
Or the Counting Numbers.
And from its name, it's clear. We call them Natural Numbers or
Counting Numbers because these are the numbers we intuitively use for counting.
When I give you something like this and ask how many,
you say one, two, three.
So, if we wanted to represent this on the number line,
we'd find that we put them, for example, like this.
We say here 1, 2, 3, to infinity.
Therefore, the Natural Numbers are the positive numbers
from 1 to infinity. This is straightforward.
Before we move to the second type of numbers, let's see
the relationship between the Properties of Numbers and the Natural Numbers.
If we look at the Natural Numbers, we'll find that out of the 12 properties
we talked about, at least three of them don't work with Natural Numbers.
These are the second property, the third, and the seventh.
The second property stated that A + 0 = A. This was the identity.
And the third property stated that A + (-A) = 0. This is the inverse
of addition. And the inverse of multiplication,
which is A * A^(-1), which means A^(-1) is 1/A.
These three properties don't work with Natural Numbers. Why?
The first one involves zero, and there are no zeros here.
Negative, there are no negatives.
Quotient, 1/A, there are no fractions here.
Therefore, these three properties...
Of course, property 10, because it's a combination of some of these,
but I, you know, removed it. There's no need for us to talk about it now,
as it's implicitly clear from the same properties because it shares them.
So, these three properties, at least, don't work with Natural Numbers.
Okay, at some stage in human history, we needed zero.
Regardless of why and when and all that, the point is, there's a number we added called zero.
The Natural Numbers together with zero are called the Whole Numbers.
By the way, the 'W' is not a formal symbol. I mean, the 'N' is formal,
a symbol in mathematics officially representing Natural Numbers.
Whole Numbers don't have... don't have an agreed-upon symbol,
but some people write it as 'W', so I'll write it to represent it,
but know that this is not quite formal.
Okay, the Whole Numbers, by adding zero to them,
solved the problem of... let me put it in another color...
solved the problem, or rather, the second property applies to them
because there is a zero here. Okay, that's good.
But properties three and seven still don't work.
There's a note here I want to mention quickly.
Some sciences, specifically, especially in computer science,
consider zero a natural number. Why?
Because in computer science and in most programming languages
- this is due to many reasons we don't want to get into details of -
counting starts from zero.
Based on that, they consider zero to be a natural number for them.
But in mainstream mathematics, zero is not a natural number.
When you don't have anything in front of you to count,
you don't say zero, one, two, three.
When I give you the numbers... I mean, I tell you, for example, count these pens,
you don't tell me zero, one, two, three. No, you start counting from one.
So, this is just a point I wanted to clarify so that if you read in some sources
that zero is a natural number, you know where this idea comes from.
Okay?
We have... let's expand the numbers a bit.
Let's go into the negatives: -1, -2, and so on to infinity in the negative direction.
And these, we call them the Integers.
The question here is, where does this 'Z' come from? Why do we denote integers
with the letter Z? Because Z comes from the word "Zahl".
Let me put it in brackets, it ends with L. I don't know if I'm pronouncing it correctly or not. It's Z-A-H-L.
It's actually a German word, German, and it means "number"
(specifically the whole numbers or integer count), and the Z comes from that.
Of course, it's clear that the Whole Numbers... sorry, the Integers
solved for me the problem, or solved the third property.
Because now there are negatives.
Okay.
Then we said we have fractions.
By the way, what I'm saying now is not the historical order of discovering numbers.
No, I just mean the order I'm explaining is aligned with the properties, nothing more.
But of course, fractions were known even before zero in some civilizations.
So the order here is not meant to be the chronological order of discovering these numbers.
Okay.
Here, for example, we say 1.5, or we can represent it as 3/2.
Here, for example, 0.5, we represent it, for example, as 1/2.
What we just mentioned, they are called fractions or quotients,
and this is the last type I have in numbers, in... I mean, not the very last,
but the last in this part. We call them Quotients.
Or the Rational Numbers.
We'll get to the "rational" part in a bit.
There are a few things here that are very important
about quotients that we need to be aware of.
First thing, quotients are not just the fractions between integers.
No, the integers themselves, including zero, are considered quotients.
What is a quotient? A quotient is any number
that you can put in the form of a ratio.
And hence the word "rational," which comes from "ratio."
Therefore, 1.5, you can put it as 3/2. 0.5 is 1/2.
2, you can put it as 2/1.
Zero is 0/3. -2 is -2/1.
Therefore, everything you see on the number line is a quotient,
because it can be put in the rational form.
This is the first point.
The second point, there are numbers that are repeating decimals.
For example, like 0.3333 and so on. Of course, you can write this like this.
Is this number rational or not rational?
It is rational. Regardless of the fact that it's a repeating decimal
and its decimal part doesn't end, it keeps going on here to infinity,
but it is rational. Why? Because I can put it in this form.
1/3, when you divide 1 by 3, you get this form.
You get a repeating decimal like this. Therefore, a number like this
is considered rational because it can be put in the form of the quotient.
Keep this part in mind because I'll need it later.
Okay, it's clear, of course, that the rational numbers or quotients
solved this problem for me because here I started dealing with fractions.
This is great.
At this stage, you might say, where's the problem? There's no problem.
I have... we're done. Here, the number line is complete.
I have four types of numbers to which... of course, the rest of the properties
already work starting from the Natural Numbers. We just had a problem with these three.
We solved them with the three new types of numbers, and it seems clear, we're done. The properties work.
But in reality, there is a situation that messed up this whole thing for me.
There's a certain type of number that started causing problems.
Like what, for example? Like... no, these need to be put in another color.
Like who, for example?
Pi (π).
And Tau (τ).
Let me put Tau for you, I mean, we might talk about it later, God willing.
They are... Tau, which is... Pi * 2.
And e, and the Golden Ratio (φ), and the square root of 2 (√2).
The numbers we see before us here, all of them,
cannot be put in the quotient form.
Therefore, they are not rational.
And because they weren't rational, they couldn't find a name for them
other than Irrational.
What does this mean?
It means these numbers - and these are not the only ones,
there are many, infinitely many -
cannot be put in this form.
Why?
Because they are non-repeating decimals,
meaning there's no pattern that repeats.
For example, if you look at 1/3, it has 0.3... 3333 repeats.
There are other numbers, for instance, you might have 213, 213, 213.
As long as there's a pattern, no matter how many digits are in the pattern,
that repeats, then it's rational. I can represent it as a quotient.
The problem with these gentlemen here is that they are fractions,
or rather decimals, not integers, and they are non-repeating decimals,
but they have no pattern.
Meaning, let's take √2 for example, it's the easiest.
If we look at it, for example, I have it written here on the margin,
the value of √2, when you represent it, you'll find it's
1.414213562...
These do not have any kind of pattern, and they keep going on like this
to infinity with strange, jumbled numbers.
Nothing repeats.
And that's why √2 cannot be represented... neither it, nor e, nor Pi, nor Tau,
nor the Golden Ratio, nor many numbers considered irrational numbers...
they cannot be represented in the form of a ratio. Therefore, we call them irrational,
the opposite of rational, which means ratio.
Okay.
So that we are also... as we got used to, when we have something,
we need to see its proof. So let's prove...
Of course, the proof for Pi and e, to prove they are irrational,
is a bit complicated. We'll talk about them, God willing, later in upcoming videos,
the upcoming videos, in detail. But √2 is easy, we can finish it quickly.
So, we will now do the proof that √2 is not rational, it is irrational.
Okay.
How do I prove that √2... let's even... let's work here...
that √2 is irrational?
The method I will use in this proof... of course, there are about, say, 30 or 40 ways
you can prove that √2 is irrational.
But we will only work through one example of them.
This example uses a proof technique called Proof by Contradiction.
Meaning, proof by contradiction.
If you plan to have a career in mathematics, you need to pay attention to this part
because it's one of the very famous techniques in proofs in mathematics.
What does this mean?
It means you want to prove that √2, for example, is irrational.
To prove it's irrational, the easiest way is to assume it is rational,
and keep digging around it down there until you find a contradiction,
until you find a conflict.
As soon as you find a contradiction with the assumption that it's rational,
it means it must be irrational.
That's it, that's the whole thing simply.
Okay.
For the square root to be rational, it must be possible to put it in this form.
Meaning, when you take the square root of a number like 2,
you get a number you can represent as an integer over an integer.
Okay.
And I will also assume that this integer... of course, I know this is not correct.
I want to prove now that this is not correct in a bit.
There's another important thing I must mention about the fraction...
about the quotient before me.
That the form before me is in its simplest form, meaning it's already
simplified to the end, meaning there is no...
no common divisor or factor.
Meaning, you can't simplify it further. For example, 2/4, no, this is not like that.
No, you simplify it first, put it as 1/2. So I'm assuming that the form before me
is already simplified to its simplest possible form. Therefore,
there are no common factors between them. Okay.
Let's continue working. Let's first get rid of the square root.
So, this... let's put this here.
Let's say it's (P/Q)² = 2. I squared it to get rid of the square root.
From which, P²/Q² = 2.
And from that, P² = 2 * Q². And here we pause for a moment.
This P here is thus even.
P is even.
How did I know? From the 2 here.
P² is equal to a number multiplied by 2.
As long as this number is multiplied by 2, it means P² is divisible by 2.
And since it's divisible by 2, it must be even. But that's P².
Any square whose value is even, its root must have been even. Meaning, 16.
16 was 4 squared. So 16 is even (square) and 4 is even (root).
So, since P² is even, then P is even.
And since P is even, then P can be written in the form... this form.
= 2k. K is any number, multiplied by 2 gives me P.
So I assume P is equal to K multiplied by 2. Okay? Because it's even.
I'll take this form and go back and put it into this equation.
We'll replace P with 2k. So, (2k)²
= 2 * Q².
Okay.
This means that 4k² = 2Q².
Cancel the 2 with the 4 here, you're left with 2k² = Q².
Q² equals a number multiplied by 2, so Q² is even.
And since Q² is even, then Q is even.
When I have P being even (an even number) and Q being even (an even number),
it means that there is at least one common divisor between them, which is 2.
What does P being even mean? For example, P is 4, and this one is, say, 6. For example.
So this is the quotient. Okay?
This means that P can be simplified... I divide by 2, so this becomes 2,
and I divide 6 by 2, which gives me 3.
This means that since both are even, there must be at least one common divisor
between them, which is 2. And this is my contradiction, because I assumed here from the beginning,
I started on the basis that they are already in the simplest form, there's no common divisor between them.
And this is the proof by contradiction.
I started by assuming that √2 equals a quotient, and when I followed this assumption,
I found a contradiction at the end.
Therefore, this assumption is wrong. Consequently, this cannot possibly be true.
And thus, √2 is an irrational number.
Okay.
The question here is, what's the problem with this?
This thing in itself... of course, it's a big problem,
but it doesn't concern me right now.
Dealing with irrational numbers in themselves is a big topic
we don't want to get into the details of.
I want to understand now, what is the relationship between this
and the problems in the properties of numbers from 1 to 12?
Let's look at this table, and what I mean will become clear.
Okay.
Here are the 12 properties I have.
The first type of numbers was the Natural Numbers, and these are
the properties that work with them and those that don't work with them.
When we added zero to the Natural Numbers, we got the Whole Numbers,
and here are their properties.
So, the second property differentiates between Whole Numbers and Natural Numbers.
And when we added negative numbers to the Whole Numbers, we got the Integers.
And here are the properties that align with Integers.
It's clear that the third property differentiates between Integers and Whole Numbers.
And when we added... sorry, when we added quotients, we got...
the quotients or the rational numbers. And here are their properties.
It's clear that the seventh property differentiates between quotients
or rational numbers and the integers.
So it's clear we are moving up a ladder like this.
We add a type of number, and there's a property that distinguishes
between the new set of numbers and the set before it.
And not only that, each set is a part of the larger set than it.
Suddenly, the irrational numbers appeared to me.
I didn't invent them; I was confronted by them. Meaning, we didn't make up something
called √2; it already existed. We just didn't know how to work with it.
e, e is Euler's number. Pi (π), these are things that exist. Meaning, we ourselves wish
we had only rational numbers.
I mean, people spent... many people dedicated their lives trying to find a fixed value
for these numbers and put them in quotient form, but they couldn't. Nobody knows how to do that.
Therefore, this is a problem we were confronted with.
And not only that.
And this is the big problem. They do not belong to the quotients,
nor are the quotients part of them. They are like a separate set on their own.
And not only that.
The same properties, all of them, from 1 to 12, that work with rational numbers,
are the exact same properties that work exactly with irrational numbers.
Therefore, I don't have any type of property that distinguishes between these two large sets.
Meaning, if we wanted to put this matter in a Venn diagram, it would look like this.
Here is N, the Natural Numbers.
Add zero to them, you get W.
Add negative numbers to them, you get Q...
sorry, you get Z, which is the Integers.
Add quotients to them, you get Q.
The irrational numbers are a separate group here, which we call Irrational Numbers.
It's a large group, its size is infinite.
And properties 1 to 12 apply to Q.
And properties 1 to 12 apply to the irrational numbers.
Therefore, I cannot use these properties to find the value of √2.
Keep in mind.
All I proved in the previous proof was that there is no Q, no rational number,
that when I square it, gives me 2.
What I proved here is that x² = (P/Q)² = 2... this situation doesn't exist.
There's no quotient I can square to get 2. This is all I proved.
Which is this, from here.
And I said it's here, among the irrational numbers, but I can't prove it.
I don't have anything from properties 1 to 12, which are the same properties
I used in this proof, I can't use them here to say what the value of √2 is.
I know there is a value for √2.
The fact that I have a symbol called √2...
means it has a value. Not only that, geometry tells me there's something called √2.
Meaning, if we went to Pythagoras,
if I have a right triangle where these two sides are the unit (1),
this must be √2.
This is what Pythagoras says.
Therefore, I have a value in geometry telling me there's something called √2.
All I proved is that this √2 is not a quotient, but I didn't prove its value
as an irrational number. I couldn't even prove it exists basically (algebraically using properties 1-12).
And this is the problem. I hope it's clear.
Of course, there could have been a simple solution: we add another property
that can... Ah, of course, before I forget, the group... this whole group is called Real Numbers.
The story of this course is all about the topic of Real Numbers.
As we said, I could add another property and deal with it, live my life with it,
just like I kept adding properties and numbers. Maybe I just add a property for irrational numbers.
But the problem is that if I add a property for irrational numbers,
this approach won't work because...
the property I would add here would conflict with something else later on.
I mean, it would clash with another mathematical concept somewhere else.
Therefore, mathematicians like things to be smooth and consistent.
Meaning, when I add a rule here, it must work everywhere.
It's not acceptable to add a rule in one place or a property in a specific place
that contradicts a rule or law in another place.
If I did that with irrational numbers, it would lead to problems.
For example, what is this? Square root of -1 (√-1).
Give me the value of √-1. This is neither a quotient nor irrational.
Should I add a property for it too? No.
Therefore, the author concluded that the solution to this whole dilemma
lies neither in studying numbers nor in studying the properties of numbers from the start.
And this is the topic we will start talking about in the upcoming videos,
God willing, or starting from the next video, which is our discussion about Functions.
And that the solution and our understanding of Real Numbers will be
in studying something else entirely, not the numbers.
See you in the next video, God willing. Goodbye.