Peace be upon you
This video will be a preview of the topic we will talk about in the next course
Which is
Calculus
We know calculus as
Differentiation and
Integration
How did 'differentiation and integration'
end up being called something like 'calculus'?
Let's clear up this naming confusion first
and then we'll continue our discussion.
Calculus is two main parts
One is called
Differential
Calculus
The other is
Integral
Calculus
In brief, both of them are called calculus
Differentiation or differential Calculus
And integration or integral calculus
Before we leave this part
I want to say something else, there are many people who think that you have to learn differentiation first to learn integration
and that integration is based on differentiation, and this is not true at all
you can learn integration before differentiation, both are considered to be the same subject
and in a certain example they are considered opposite to each other
but it is not a condition to learn this first and then this
and in most of the courses, including the one we will be working on today
we will be working on differentiation and then integration, but this is not a condition
in fact, one of the two who wrote the calculus published the integration first before differentiation
and I think that 100-200 years after the creation of the calculus, most books talked about both separately
they wrote the integration and then the differentiation, there was no problem at all
I just wanted to clarify this part initially
ok
so what does calculus mean?
there are many people who enter a course like this and then they draw a graph and say that calculus is the rate of change
and that it is the slope of the tangent line of a point on a curve
and that integration is the area below the curve or part of the curve
and if they want to go deeper into the subject, they will give you the example of velocity
and the change of distance over time
and acceleration which is the change of velocity over time
and so on
I think that this is a bit early
I mean, we can't get into this in a stage like this
if we were to give an example that is more in depth and simpler to understand
so that we know what calculus is about
and frankly, the example of calculating the calculus in the framework that I just mentioned
I think it is not very accurate
because these are tools
that calculus has
but the problem that calculus deals with is what I need to talk about a little
ok
I will say one sentence about calculus before moving on to the historical part that explains the circumstances of the creation of calculus
if I wanted to give a definition of calculus, I can say that I personally call it the art of dealing with narrow spaces
ok
so, keep this sentence in your mind
now, it will be clear after a while
when we mention the word calculus
there are two names that appear instantly
Isaac Newton and Gottfried Leibniz
Isaac Newton is the most famous mathematician in the world
he is an English scientist
he is the king of gravity for at least 200 years
Newton's laws
he has achievements in optics and other things like that
and he invented calculus
Leibniz is less famous than him
although he is also a very respected scientist
he is a German scientist
he studied law in Germany
then he moved to France
he studied mathematics
he liked it a little
he continued with it
and then he invented calculus
he did not invent calculus only
he had achievements in other things
including the invention of the binary system of zero and one
which we are using today in computer systems
this was in the second half of the 17th century
the question here is what makes two scientists invent calculus at the same time
of course, when Leibniz and Newton started to spread their words about calculus
Europe, literally, before calculus
or before Leibniz and Newton started to talk about their achievements in calculus
was something
and after calculus was something else
I personally am convinced that
the real European rise started with calculus
calculus without exaggeration
is the foundation of modern science
which you see around you today
without calculus you really go back to technology
until the beginning of the 18th century
so calculus is an important subject
you have to study it in depth
because any career you want to persue: Physics, Engineering
or any kind of science
even if it has advanced things in mathematics
calculus is the thing that takes all of that
okay
something of importance
when someone like Newton or Leibniz says
we invented calculus
Europe and its scientific community
stood on their feet
and there was a big fight between the two
which of them had the right to claim that they invented calculus
Newton says I did it
Leibniz says I did it
and a debate occurred between the two of them
and there was a huge debate in the scientific community in Europe
for decades
even after the death of Leibniz and Newton
to say who really invented calculus
and historians settled that Newton and Leibniz invented calculus independently
and of course there were many evidences of this
one of them was the difference in timing
and the notes they wrote
and the most important difference
or the most important point that supported
the idea that the two of them did it separately
is that the two
although they reached the same result at the end in calculus
but the approach of each one of them was completely different
Newton and Leibniz looked at calculus from two completely different perspectives
and this is an important point you should keep in mind
because sometimes when we talk about calculus
we look at it from this perspective
which is the rate of change
of course the rate of change is the most important thing
and we take it only in physics
and it adjusts the velocity and acceleration
and the end of the subject
calculus is very important
you will be surprised that it is used strongly in finance and economics
so calculus is much wider than this perspective
which we sometimes gather ourselves in
let's go back to the most important question
what makes someone like Newton
someone like Leibniz
living in two different countries
think about something important
like calculus
and almost at the same time
calculus was not a luxury
meaning that Newton and Leibniz were not sitting idle
and they said let's make something new
so they made calculus
no
and this is a very important point
you should keep in mind
calculus was a cure for a problem already existing
and this problem reached a stage
that science, especially physics
became a burden that cannot move
and this problem existed for thousands of years
to understand this problem
let's go back to the example I mentioned
which is a fundamental one
in explaining what is the problem of calculus
this example is from the days of the Greeks
specifically Archimedes
you know that the Greeks were fascinated by geometry
geometry was not part of mathematics
but this was their life in geometry
so Archimedes was trying to calculate an example
to calculate the area of the circle
of course when I say that Archimedes was trying to calculate the area of the circle
I am very simplifying what Archimedes was doing
Archimedes was trying to find the nearest value of pi
to calculate the area of the circle and its circumference
but for simplicity we will say that he wanted to calculate the area of the circle
and for simplicity we will not take the approach that they all did
because his approach is big
and there are many details
we will just take a specific part from it
to take me to the problem that preceded him
and after that Newton and Leibniz solved it
and they solved it with calculus
to make this clear
let's go to the computer
and see the model in GeoGebra
how it looks
and try to solve the problem
or try to represent what Archimedes did
about 200 years before the birth
this is the circle we will work on
and we want to see what Archimedes did
to calculate its area
Archimedes did not have a way to calculate the area of the circle
because it is a curve
they could calculate the area and circumference of shapes
made up of straight lines
like triangles, squares, rectangles, polygons, etc.
so he said let's put a shape of these straight shapes
that we can calculate its area
and put it inside the circle so that it occupies the largest space of the circle
and thus it is almost the area of the circle
so he put a hexagon
or a polygon of 6 sides
why did he start with a hexagon?
because the hexagon has a very important symmetry
each of the rectangles in front of you
from the hexagon
equals half the diameter of the circle
that surrounds it from the 6 angles
this is something that distinguishes the hexagon
that's why he started from the hexagon
because it provides him with very important information
that facilitates the proof that he was working with
as we said there are many details in the work of Archimedes
in the pie group or the circumference group
or in the area of the circle
we will not talk about it
I just care about a specific part
in clarifying the problem that the calculus is trying to solve
if we look at this hexagon
it occupies a space that is not necessarily of the circle
we have some simple things here
which are the white parts
we can
increase the accuracy of the area
if we increase the number of rectangles of the polygon
so we started with 6
and now we have another polygon
let's make it of 12 sides
and here we want to look at something
the first side
or the hexagon
when it was 6 sides
is longer than each side in the polygon
when it was 12 sides
ok
the distance between the two vertices
as a result of the polygon's radius being short
the distance between the two vertices got smaller
instead of the distance between the two vertices
as you can see
the distance between the two vertices is less than ti
approximately the half
or more precisely
half
keep in mind
that we will go back to this part later
I still have a white part
it is true that my accuracy of the area has increased
but I still have a white part here
I didn't cover it up
ok
if I increased the number of rectangles of the polygon
I started with 6
now it is 12
let's make it 24
now it is clear that we have almost finished the whole circle
but I said almost
why?
because even though you may not be able to keep track of it
there are still white parts
and to see these white parts
if we zoom in
it can be more clear
you will notice that the white distance here has increased
not only increased
you will notice that these two points
after they were very close to each other
they got apart
and this is a very important point
after I zoomed in
the distance between the two points increased
and I was able to show you that this white part is present
no, there is a part of the circle
we still haven't been able to calculate its area
ok
if we increase it again
we have increased the number of the polygon
and we made it 48
ah, no
we have almost finished the whole circle
but if you focus a little here
you will find that there is still a white space here
and if we zoom in more
you will notice that every time I zoom in
these two points are far apart
I stretch them
and the white space here appears in front of me
and this is something
that is very important
ok
let's see what we did
first we put the hexagon
which is 6
6 sides
then we made them 12 sides
we covered a larger area
then we made 48 sides
then we made
no, it was 6, 12, 24
then 48
in conclusion, it is clear here
that no matter how much we increase the number of sides of the polygon
there will always be a part of the circle
that we still haven't been able to cover with the area
because we are still looking for a space
because any two points
no matter how close they are to each other
I can zoom in on them
and show you that there is a large space between them
we will talk about this topic in detail later
the question here is when
the length of this polygon
or the width of this polygon
covers the circle
without a gap
without this white space
the answer is when this point sticks to this point
so that the length of the polygon's radius is the same as the point
it is just a point on the circle
the problem is that this is mathematically impossible
why?
let's go to the board and see
I think we understood what Archimedes was trying to do
and we understood that his problem is that no matter how much the number of sides is increased
he will always have a side
that leaves a space
between him and the circle
because the circle is curved
and the polygon is a straight line
and we said that it is impossible
for this polygon to stick to the circle
and remove all the space to calculate it
other than when this point sticks to this point
the problem is that in order for this to happen
we must understand how the real numbers work
because here there is a contradiction
if we look at it
let's talk about the natural numbers
let's say here is 0
and here is 1
and here is 2
and here is 3
and here we are talking about natural numbers
if I told you
what are the numbers between 1 and 3
how many will you tell me?
you will tell me 2
and your answer will be 100% correct
why?
because the natural numbers have only the whole numbers
the positive ones
in this situation we are not dealing with natural numbers
we are dealing with the set of natural numbers
a set of real numbers
and the set of real numbers is different from the set of natural numbers
because if I told you what in the set of real numbers is between 1 and 3
you will tell me 2
1.5
2.5
2.3
2.999999999
it's infinity
the number of numbers between 1 and 3
infinity
the number of numbers between 1 and 2
the number of numbers between any 2 numbers
No matter how small the distance between them is on the real numbers line, it's infinity.
Any two points you can put, I can zoom in on them, as I did in the program a while ago,
and I can get an infinite number of numbers between them, no matter how small the distance between them is.
The same problem here.
To connect this point to this point, so that this line is the distance between two points on the circle,
and these two points don't have anything between them, that's impossible, because there are no points between real numbers.
And this was the problem.  That is the calculus.
Archimedes imagined something, and gave it a name for a while, not the name we will use later,
but he imagined that there is a number, small, but not zero.
We will return to this concept later, but keep this in mind.
This problem was,
it existed for a long time, as we said, Archimedes, and it remained with the scientists for a long time.
When did we get a serious work to solve this problem?
This was in the first half of the 17th century.
You have scientists like Kepler, Descartes, Fermat, Pascal, all of them tried to solve this problem.
They were trying to solve the problem that we talked about at the beginning of the video,
which is the second problem.
The second problem is the tangent line between the point on the curve and the area below the curve.
This problem is this problem.
How? We will see this in the course.
Specifically, this problem, or solving this problem,
it would be easy if I could act in this problem,
because the only constraint in getting this tangent line and the area below the curve,
is to reach the point, or the distance between the two points,
so that there is nothing between them.
And the number of points is not allowed.
As we said, there are many scientists who tried this problem,
and some of their techniques worked.
Their problem was that they were isolated,
meaning that this technique works in this graph, but it does not work in another graph,
or it works in this type of problem, but it does not work in other problems,
or it makes errors in this case, and in the other case, it does not make errors.
So, the problem was not consistent, and it was not possible to solve it,
and it was not something that worked on all the graphs.
And here is the achievement of Newton and Leibniz.
Newton and Leibniz studied the experiments they did,
which they did with very high accuracy and very focused,
and they benefited from all the errors they made,
and they collected all this and came up with the technique called calculus,
specifically integration and differentiation.
Their problem was that their foundation was not strong.
The tool that was working, really, made a revolution in the scientific community,
in Europe, because without it, physics was stuck,
because all the modern problems of physics depend on the rate of change,
depend on irregular shapes,
traditional mathematics such as arithmetic, algebra, geometry, and trigonometry
could not solve the real problems in the real world.
So, physics was really stuck in this stage.
So, calculus was the solution,
and that is why I always say that if Newton and Leibniz had not invented it,
someone else would have invented it.
One of these scientists who worked on these things would have reached a solution in the end,
because physics would not have moved forward if calculus had not appeared.
As we said, Newton and Leibniz made the technique,
but the foundation that this technique had in terms of mathematical fundamentals
and mathematical reasoning was very, very weak,
because they could not find a solution.
So, they came up with a new idea,
and it was Leibniz,
he made a shortcut,
he said,
we cannot solve this problem,
so we invented a new term,
they took the same idea from Archimedes,
but they gave it a very funny name,
it is called
infinitesimal numbers,
or quantities.
What does it mean?
This group says that there is a very, very small number,
smaller than anything you can imagine,
and smaller than anything you can measure,
but it is larger than zero,
it is still in the positive numbers.
What is this number? We do not know.
It exists.
And this was the problem in the calculus of Newton and Leibniz.
Of course, all mathematics scholars and all philosophers
who were present at that time
criticized this concept,
because there is nothing to be said about it,
there is nothing,
you cannot hold something in your hand,
you cannot put an important branch in mathematics
on a strange concept like this.
But calculus was working,
you come to hold the equation of calculus,
and apply it, and it is full working,
but the foundation had a big problem.
It had a big problem to the extent that there was a very famous person called Berkeley,
who wrote an article after Newton and Leibniz died,
by about 10 or 20, maybe 30 years,
in which the foundation of calculus was criticized very heavily.
Maybe this is one of the most critical points
that the foundation of calculus had to deal with.
And he described these infinitesimal numbers,
and he called them the ghosts of the departed quantities.
Finally, I want to say that Newton and Leibniz
are talking about a number that died,
and we are now dealing with its absence,
or I mean, it is exactly what he meant,
of course, there was a big problem in this subject.
This problem was solved later.
We will come to this subject in a little while.
In the late 17th century and the beginning of the 18th century,
or in the first half of the 18th century,
a group of scientists appeared
who contributed to the development of calculus
and the development of mathematics in general,
but I only care about three of them here.
Taylor, Euler, and Fourier.
These three had contributions to mathematics in general,
but they were three common factors
that taught a lot in two parts,
which are the sequences
and the series.
Of course, the sequences and the series
are not new concepts,
they did not appear in the 17th and 18th centuries,
but they were from the days of Fonacci,
before that, for example, 300 or 400 years ago.
So, these are old concepts,
but with the advent of calculus,
they started to look at sequences and series in a different way,
and they started to talk about them in a deeper way
in the infinite series.
This led to the emergence of another concept,
which we will talk about later,
which corrected the infinitesimal numbers.
And here comes the role of the next scientist,
who is called Cauchy,
and this was a French scientist.
He was in the late 18th century
and in the beginning of the century,
or in the first half of the 19th century.
Cauchy was the first to present a concept,
let's put it here,
because this is its place,
the concept of limits,
and we put this in a square.
Limits are the foundation
on which calculus is drawn.
Limits are the concept
that replaced the infinitesimal numbers.
And limits were formed
after a great development in mathematics,
and one of the most important things
that led Cauchy to be able to understand the concept of limits
and present it,
is the sequence of the series.
That's why I mentioned it,
one of the most important things in calculus,
because it has a very strong impact on the limit.
Cauchy was the first to present,
or to talk about the limit,
more than 130 years after the calculus
that Newton and Leibniz did.
To the extent that some people consider Cauchy
to be the real inventor,
or the real discoverer of calculus,
because he presented the concept of limits.
Because for many people,
limits are calculus.
The differentiation and integration of the limits,
is just a tool that you use
to solve the physics problems
or the mathematical problems that you have.
But the concept,
the foundation,
the mathematical reasoning of calculus,
is almost exclusive in the limits.
Understanding the limits is not easy.
Understanding the limits requires work from you,
because if you understand it,
the rest will be a piece of cake.
The infinitesimals numbers began to be shaken,
Until a German scientist came after Cauchy and refined Cauchy's limits.
because Cauchy's limits had ambiguity,
so he refined it,
and this was the last nail in the infinitesimals numbers' coffin.
And the limits took off.
The limits were trying to solve this problem,
and they really did.
After all this,
in the late 18th century,
and the beginnings of the 19th century,
no, sorry,
in the late 19th century,
and the beginning of the 20th century,
or the first period of the 20th century,
another scientist appeared.
This man in particular,
I have to write his name,
this man's name is
George Cantor.
George Cantor,
if we had not made a film of his life,
now we must make a film of it.
This man's life story was a tragedy,
it was very exciting and sad,
and unfortunately,
it is a tragedy to some extent.
This man began to talk about very important theories in this part.
This man, in the end,
he is the boss of real numbers
he did not talk about the limit specifically,
or his calculations were not in the specific limits,
his calculations were in changing the point of view of people in mathematics,
to numbers,
and specifically in real numbers,
which directly affects people's understanding of limits.
This man presented the set theory,
number theory,
the continuum,
the cardinality,
the cardinality of the continuum,
the nested intervals,
the amount of theorems this man made,
and presented a new door in mathematics,
which we now call set theory.
The problem is that when he presented all these concepts at the beginning,
no one expressed it,
even though he was a well-known scientist,
he was originally a German scientist,
but he was born in Russia and returned to Germany after that,
and studied mathematics in famous German universities.
But when he started talking about set theories,
no one cared.
The problem was that they started attacking him to the extent that he was humiliated,
and stopped his career in many stages,
because he had the opportunity to go and hold a post at the Berlin University,
and they stopped his teacher, who was not convinced of his theories.
This teacher was one of the most negatively affected people in his life,
he was even called the corrupt of the youth,
which means that he is a messed-up guy,
and he is a boy who mess-up the youth around him,
because he was teaching these techniques to his colleagues in mathematics.
The situation became very bad with him,
to the extent that he entered depression,
and he spent the last 15 or 20 years of his life moving from mental institute to mental institute.
People have frustrated the man in his life.
His son died at that time, and his condition deteriorated more,
and he was going out and working a little,
and he get more confused,
and he go to another institute.
In the end, the man got to a point where here retired from mathematics
and he went to teach philosophy,
and then he left philosophy and taught literature,
and specialized in the literature of the time of Shakespeare and Queen Elizabeth,
and then he returned to mathematics again.
In the end, the man remained in mental institue,
and out of mental institue,
until he died in the last one of them,
he entered about 4 or 5 times,
and died in the end in a mental institue in 1918.
In the near end of his life,
people began to realize that this man was not crazy,
this man was speaking very important words,
and today,
one of the most important branches of mathematics,
and one of the most important branches of mathematics,
which is very advanced,
is the theories that this man is the founder of.
Why do we say this?
This man changed people's understanding of real numbers,
and as long as your understanding of real numbers changes,
your understanding of limits changes,
and if you want to understand limits correctly,
you must understand the next point,
which is the properties of,
I will not write real numbers here,
I will write numbers in general.
This is our course.
We will talk at the beginning about the properties of numbers,
then we will talk about functions,
of course, functions are the most important concept in mathematics in general,
so we will talk about functions,
I will write it here,
functions,
so we will talk here,
we will talk about functions,
and from functions we will talk about limits,
and from limits we will talk about differentiation and integration,
sequences and series are in different places in the course,
we will talk about complex numbers,
which is also related to the properties of numbers,
because they provide us with a new type of numbers,
so,
the purpose of this introduction was to show you that calculus is not just differentiation and integration,
and not just limits,
they are many things in each other,
because calculus as a subject is part of the largest branch in mathematics,
called real analysis,
and this is one of the very important fields in mathematics,
we do not have to go into it,
but at least we should understand this frame very well,
if you want to have a strong future in any study in physics,
and any study in engineering,
or of course,
I am sure it is in any advanced mathematics,
you will work in it, God willing, in the future,
we come to the source that we will work from in this course,
of course, there are many books,
the most famous book is considered as an introduction to calculus and real analysis,
a book by an American scientist named Michael Spivak,
I think this man is still alive, he was born in 1940,
he wrote the book that we will work from,
or the first copy or version of it,
he was 67,
he was 27 years old,
this is the year he took his PhD,
although he wrote this book when he was very young,
as I told you, this book is considered the calculus book for many people,
they consider that in order to study calculus,
you must read this book at a certain stage in your life,
in order to keep your name,
this is the book that we will work from, God willing,
see you in the next video,
peace be upon you.