Alright, let's get started.
So, I'm first going to just go through a review of what we've done so far.
What's the story so far? Well,
the first sort of theme that we've treated is that groups are everywhere.
We've defined these things abstractly, but really, they're very, very concrete.
If you're ever trying to figure out what should be true in general of a group, you have a lot of great examples to look at to test your ideas on.
So for instance, one of our first examples was GLNR.
Another example we saw was the symmetric group on N letters.
And a third example we saw was the um uh group of integers under addition.
So, when I just write Z, I really mean integers with addition.
And another of the themes that that we hinted at, but haven't treated in detail so far is that these things uh arise as the structure preserving bijections of something.
So, what are the structure preserving things here? Well, this is the structure preserving bijections for Rn with its linear structure.
This is just the uh the set of structure preserving uh bijections on a set of n elements with just its set structure, no additional structure.
And Z, there are a lot of ways of sort of realizing Z as the symmetries of something.
So another sort of thing that we'll be talking about is symmetries of geometric objects.
So, this is just a hint at something that I'm not going to treat in detail now, but which will be a recurring theme. If I take um the sort of infinite um directed graph
where I have just uh a series of vertices, an infinite number of vertices extending out in both directions and I just have directed arrows, then the symmetries of this thing, well, all I can do is shift it by a certain amount.
Again, we'll treat that in greater detail later.
Another theme we've discussed is that um given a group, there are a whole bunch of other groups that sort of come out of that group.
Um, so making new groups out of old.
And you should really think of this as being a very familiar sort of procedure. You've seen this sort of thing in great detail in linear algebra.
You've seen subspaces of a given vector space and that's the sort of thing that, you know, we saw with subgroups being part of a group.
Um, we we saw things like um the cyclic subgroup generated by an element. Well, that's sort of like having the vector space generated by a single vector.
Um, and there'll be a few other things that we'll see later in the course like products of spaces corresponding or being analogous to products of groups.
And then finally, um something that I'll start talking about today. We know that um stuff like Ho Rn Rn has a vector space structure on it.
Well, likewise, the uh given a group, the set of morphisms between G and itself that are bijective form a group.
And so we have a lot of analogy analogies and whenever you want to think about what's going on here, you can often think back, you can often use a lot of your intuitions from linear algebra.
A third theme that we've looked at,
is that in some cases you can actually classify the subgroups of a given group.
So last time we considered the subgroups of Z.
Now, the argument we used to show that um every subgroup of Z is of the form BZ looked innocuous, but it's actually a very significant argument. Again, it's something that's going to come back to Honda, so it's a very good idea to familiarize yourself well with that argument.
Um, just recall that basically what we did is we took a subgroup, we said, well, if it's non zero, then there must be some smallest positive integer in it.
And then we showed using the Euclidean algorithm that every element of the group must be a form uh of the form uh an integer times that smallest positive integer.
in the subgroup. So, um in general though, it's very, very difficult to study the subgroup structure of a given group, but it's also very, very important.
Um, then another thing that we looked at was
particular cyclic subgroups. So I'll just refresh your memory on that.
So if I have a group and I have an element of that group, I can consider the set of all powers of that element and that forms a subgroup.
So, here are a couple of examples. If I take in GLNR, the element 1101,
then sorry, GL2R, thank you very much. N is 2.
Um, the cyclic subgroup generated by this thing, well, it's not hard to see that the powers of this thing all look like 1 N 0 1.
Uh, this you can prove usually by induction for instance.
Um, people who aren't familiar with mathematical induction maybe should see me after class.
Um, so this is ranging over all integers.
So these are these are a lot of the sorts of themes we've seen so far.
And and so so when when you have infinitely many elements in the uh in the cyclic subgroup generated by a given element, you say that that element has infinite order.
Of course, quite often, uh elements will not have infinite order. Quite often, there will be just fintely many distinct powers of something. For instance, if I just take again in GL2R, um minus the identity matrix, then this thing has order two.
I square it and I get the identity matrix.
Sorry?
Okay.
So the first new theme that we're going to talk about today is that of isomorphism.
So let's try a very sort of simple way of of starting to understand isomorphism.
Um, so let's consider a couple of different groups.
So the first group, let's consider, call it g1, we'll make this plus or minus one plus or minus I.
viewed as uh a subgroup of C star, which is notation for the non-zero complex numbers equipped with multiplication as the group operation.
So it's just a very simple thing. Um, I mean this is just the powers of I square root of -1 K running through K uh 0 through 3.
Another group, we'll consider is the cyclic subgroup of S4 symmetric group on four letters generated by
something I'll call row.
And well, here's a way of describing what it does. It sort of cycles the things around. It cycles them. So one goes to two, two goes to three, three goes to four, four goes to one.
In a shorthand we'll be introducing uh eventually, this might be written 1, two, three, four. Now you don't have to worry about that, but it's an easy way of just sort of coding what this permutation is.
Um and it's not hard to see that for instance, well, row squared is certainly not either the identity or row.
You can see that because if you evaluate uh row composed with itself, um well, one will go to two, two will go to three. So row squared takes one to three. Um and certainly neither the identity nor row do that.
Likewise, row cubed is not one of E row row squared. by the same sort of argument or just using what we've established already and um inverting. I mean if if row cube equal row squared then for instance row would equal E, which isn't true.
Um, but because these things are just being cycled around, it's not hard to see that one will end up back at one after composing this permutation with itself four times and likewise for two, three and four. So this is just the identity.
Um, so put another way, the multiplication table for this thing, E row, row squared, row cubed just looks like E row, row squared, row cubed, then shift this row, row squared, row cubed E, row squared, row cubed E row, row cubed E row row squared.
That follows immediately from this.
But that's exactly the same thing as the multiplication table for I.
So in some sense, these are really the same group. They just have the same multiplication table, but they're relabelings of each other.
Is that fairly clear or does anybody not see that?
I guess I don't see. Okay, sure.
So I has the property that its fourth power is one.
But all the powers in between
uh that and, you know, this fourth power are not any of the previous things. So for instance,
I is not I squared is not it's minus one. It's not the same thing as one or I. Um I cube is minus I, that's not one
minus one or I. Um and so again, by the same sort of thing, when you multiply the things around, it just sort of circulates them.
So call this thing G2.
The idea is that G1 and G2 have the same multiplication table,
but with a relabeling.
So this idea of relabeling multiplication tables gets formalized in algebra under the name isomorphism.
So I'll write down a definition now.
isomorphism.
And isomorphism is a map
between two groups which is bijective and such that
it preserves the multiplication operation.
So f of X * Y is f of X * f of Y.
Where of course, over here, this is the multiplication in G1 and this is the multiplication in G2.
So this is the same sort of idea. You're just F is what's telling you how to relabel the things.
And um the idea that the multiplication table is preserved is just saying that uh f ofx * Y is the same thing as f ofx * f of y.
So, here's another example.
So in this case what's the?
So in this case, the isomorphism is given explicitly by sending powers of I, so say I to the Kth power
So explicitly,
in our case,
I send the Kth power of I to the Kth power of row.
So one gets sent to the identity, uh I gets sent to row, I squared gets sent to row squared, I cube gets sent to row cubed.
Does that mean f of I to the K?
Yeah, so
F of I to the K equals row to the K.
gives us an nice.
And a more general fact, which is a very good exercise,
which I believe is included in the exercises for today, which I'll put up on the board uh at the end of class, is the following. So, um
I'll write it as a fact now, and I'll leave part of the thing unproved and the exercise will be to fill in the gap.
So, I'm going to use some words and then I'll explain exactly what I mean by them.
So every cyclic group of order n or every two cyclic groups of order n
are isomorphic.
Um so definitions.
A cyclic group is just a group um such that there is some element in it which generates the entire group.
And isomorphic,
well we say g1 and g2 are isomorphic
if there is an isomorphism between them.
And we'll see shortly that if there's an isomorphism going one way, there's certainly one going the other way and this turns out to be a good equivalence relation, but we'll see that later.
But how do we see that? Well, um in brief, and again, you fill this, you finish this off in the uh uh assignment in the problem set. If I have g1, g2 and they're both cyclic of order N, and I have elements X1 and X2 that generate,
then the map F from g1 to g2 taking the Kth power of X1 to the Kth power of X2,
you can show is a well-defined bijection.
Specifically because X1 and X2 have the same order, and that's what the exercise is about.
And the preservation of multiplication property is fairly straightforward. That follows just from the fact that if I have X1 to the n times X2 to the M, so F X1 to the n X2 to the M,
Well, that's F X1 to the n + M, that's X2 to the n + M, and that's X2 to the n times X2 to the M.
So really all there is to check is that this thing is a well-defined bijection.
Now, um, let's talk about something which isn't cyclic. Oh, yeah.
Is there a cyclic group of order n for every n?
It turns out there is one, and it's not hard to construct one inside of SN by just taking the cycle.
So in SN, so the question is about is there is there always a cyclic group of order n?
Well, in SN, the cycle, the uh the permutation taking 1 to two, two to three, etcetera on down n - 1 to n, and then n back to one,
it's not hard to show has order n and uh so the group generated by that is a cyclic group of order n. Yes, your question.
Can you call please?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
Um in that second to the bottom board can you write F of X1 to the N times X1 to the M?
Yeah, this is X1.
Absolutely.
Any other questions?
Yeah.
on the SN thing that you just put up there, Mhm. That was to show what exactly?
So in SN, there's certainly a permutation that looks like this.
This is permutation.
And um call it sigma sub n.
And the question was, is there always a cyclic group of order n?
And so it turns out there is because if I take this permutation in SN,
and I consider the cyclic subgroup generate of SN generated by this sigma N, then this thing has order N.
Okay, is everyone caught up?
Okay, great.
So, um, let's look at a different kind of example.
Um,
example.
Well, consider the real numbers under addition
and the positive real numbers, the strictly positive real numbers under multiplication.
A priori, just looking at these things, you wouldn't necessarily expect that they'd be isomorphic.
So
But does anybody see something that witnesses an isomorphism? Yeah.
Absolutely. So,
or putting it another way,
Um, what you can do is take F from, so here's G1, here's G2.
F from g1 to g2 defined it by f ofx is E to the X.
Well, we know because of the existence of the logarithm, this is certainly a bijection has the right image and everything.
And also, we know just by basic math that E to the X + Y is E to the X * E to the Y.
So it preserves the group structure, it preserves the multiplication table.
So this is an example of a pair of isomorphic groups that are not finite and are not cyclic.
Okay, another example, returning to finite groups, but something which is not cyclic.
And this is a very useful group to sort of a very, very small but useful group to test things out on.
It's called the Klein four group and I'll give you two ways of writing it.
Klein four group.
So the first way I'll write it is um as a subset of S4.
So, two ways to write it.
So the first one, uh, call it G1.
Um, I have just the identity E.
I'll take something uh I guess I'll call um tau1 and I'll define it as follows. It'll take one to two and two back to one.
It'll also exchange three and four.
Tau 2, I'll take to be um something that exchanges
one and three and two and four.
So one goes to three, three goes to one, two goes to four, four goes to two. Is that clear?
And the final element I'll take is Tau 1 Tau 2.
And just by tracing through these things. So first I look at what Tau 2 goes to one does to one say. So Tau 2 takes one to three and then Tau 1 takes three to four.
So one goes to four.
And if I just keep on computing these things this way, I find that four goes back to one, two goes to three, three goes to two.
But it's also easy to verify that if I reverse the order, if I take tau1, if I apply tau1 to something and then tau2 to the result of that, then I get exactly the same thing.
So, just a sort of linguistic point here, we say that these things commute, tau1 and tau2 commute because tau1 tau2 equals tau2 tau1.
So, what is the group structure here? Well, what's Tau 1 squared?
It's the identity.
What's Tau 2 squared?
What's Tau 1 Tau 2 squared?
Exactly.
So the group structure is very, very simple. Each of these things if we multiply by itself, you get E.
Obviously, if you take E by any of these things, you get whatever you multiplied by back. And if I multiply tau1 by tau 2, I get tau1 tau 2 or tau 2 by tau1, I get the same thing.
What about if I multiply tau1 by tau1 tau 2?
Exactly. So if I take any of these things of order two and I multiply them by each other, I get the third.
So here's another way of writing the group.
I could just write it as the set of matrices, so in GL2R say, I could just write it as the set of matrices, well, identity matrix.
Where I just change the entries here to to minus ones.
So certainly these have um the same relevant property.
Um, if I multiply any of these things by themselves, I get the identity matrix back. And if I multiply any two of the things which have negative entries, then I get the third of the things that have negative entries.
So again, you know, they have the same multiplication table and there's a nice direct bijection. I can for instance have the bijection F
take E to the identity, Tau 1 to this, Tau 2 to this, and Tau 1 Tau 2 to this.
Okay, great.
Yes.
Why do you need to define the four elements of the group? I mean that's just given the first three where the fourth
have to be in there. Absolutely. I could have said
the group generated by tau1 tau 2.
But if I want to list all the elements in the group, then I better include tau1 tau 2.
So the question was,
did uh uh do I really need to include Tau 1 Tau 2 in this list?
Well, yes and no.
If I wanted to say, you know, just consider the group, the smallest group that contains Tau 1 and Tau 2,
Well, I could have just said Tau 1 Tau 2.
But if I want to write out the entire group explicitly, all of the elements, then I need to include Tau 1 Tau 2 and the identity.
So,
Okay, so non example.
So the client group. So I say the, and this is a confusion that that that you you often make or sort of uh
uh a shorthand that you often make in algebra and that is that if you have a couple of groups that are isomorphic, you often talk about them as if they're the same group.
So although we have two different ways of concretely realizing the client four group, because they're isomorphic, we talk about it as if there's just the client four group.
So is the client four group isomorphic to that cyclic group we started with?
question? Yes.
Is there a simple for the client group?
Pardon me? Is there a simple for the client group? Um,
I mean it's not very sta- the question is is there a symbol for the client group? Different texts will often have different short hands for it before there's a more sophisticated notion introduced.
I mean, but yeah, I mean, later on we'll see that there's a a sort of simpler way of writing in terms of things which do have a notation. Um, so just as a preview, it's a product of two cyclic groups of order two.
Yes, Peter.
I think Artin might is is Artin might use the the notation V for the client four group. So, but if you look in other texts, I'm not sure that it'll have the same notation.
But yeah, Artin might use that notation.
But so, is this are these things isomorphic?
No.
What's an easy way of seeing that they're not isomorphic?
Yeah.
Exactly.
It has So an easy way of seeing this is that I has order four, whereas the client group only has elements of maximal order two.
So here are some very, very simple ways um of checking whether things are isomorphic.
So no, um uh the former doesn't have elements of order four, whereas this does has two of them, I and minus I.
Okay.
Um,
so here are some here are some easy ways of of you know, first checking whether two groups are isomorphic or not. Obviously the these won't work in all cases.
But um
some properties to test whether groups are isomorphic.
The first one I'll list is that they have the same order.
If they're finite groups or infinite groups, they'd better have the same cardinality because there's a bijection between them.
A second thing they'd better have in common is that if one is a billion, the other had better be a billion. and vice versa.
And the third quick thing that you can easily check in a lot of cases is that G1 and G2 uh had better have the same number of elements of every order.
Yes.
Is cardinality of the group just the number of elements in it?
That's yeah,
cardinality is a synonym for number of elements.
And there's another term we use, the order of a group.
So there there there often as in as in Yeah, you can you can use them essentially interchangeably, although the term order has different meanings in other context. So order is something that's more specific to the language of groups.
But as in any sort of language, yeah, there there are often synonyms and there there's a lot of redundancy.
Okay.
So we mentioned earlier that given any group G, we can construct another group out of it by taking its symmetries.
In other words, taking bijections between the group and itself that preserve the structure on a group.
What's a name for this that we've come up with so far?
automorphism?
Exactly. So well, so last time we saw the term automorphism, but today we used the term isomorphism.
So an isomorphism between a group and itself is called an automorphism.
So here's another example or here's another sort of uh construction.
So given G, we can construct the set
denoted odd G.
So these are called automorphisms,
which is just a shorthand for isomorphisms between the group and itself.
So this is the set um well, as I said, of isomorphisms from G to G, but in the sort of impressionistic language we were using earlier, this is the symmetries of G or the structure preserving maps of G.
structure preserving bijections.
Any questions?
Okay.
So there's something that we haven't verified that we really ought to verify.
So I called this a group. This is a little problematic.
I mean, we know certainly that composites of um isomorphisms are isomorphisms because certainly the the composite will still be a bijection and uh if you have say F and g isomorphisms then
F of G FG XY is F of g of X g of Y which is FG X FGY.
And the identity is certainly there. We have just the usual identity map from G to itself and that's certainly an isomorphism.
But we're missing something and that is that inverses are still automorphisms.
And that's easy to verify, but it's something you certainly need to verify.
And um I'll give as an exercise. It's extremely easy, but it's I'll list it as one of the exercises to prove that this thing is a group.
So the thing you need to verify, the last remaining thing to verify um exercise in problem set show that the inverse of an iso uh of an automorphism is an automorphism.
Or more generally that the inverse of an isomorphism is an isomorphism.
This isn't hard to see, uh but it's worth verifying to make sure that you're comfortable with the language.
So it's going to be one of the problems I list amongst the uh um things from Artin.
Okay. Um,
let's move along to something a little different.
So, so far we we've talked about bijections which preserve the structure of a group, that preserve the multiplication operation.
But I'm going to introduce a sort of generalization of this idea. things called homomorphisms.
So for instance,
the determinant map from say GLNR to R star,
which again, per our previous notation is the non-zero elements of R with multiplication as the group operation.
Well, it's certainly a well-defined map and we know um that the determinant of AB is the determinant of A times the determinant of B by basic linear algebra.
Is this thing an isomorphism?
No.
What's an easy way of seeing that it's not an isomorphism?
Sorry?
Yeah, go ahead.
It's not one to one for example.
Um well, so yeah, I mean it's there are a lot of easy ways of seeing that that in fact GLN and R star aren't even can't possibly be isomorphic. One of them being for instance that
this is a billion and this is not.
So uh certainly debt is not one to one and in fact there can't be any isomorphism between GLNR and R star.
Um but nonetheless it does preserve the group structure.
There can be no bijection.
There can be bijections. In fact, these two have the same cardinality, but you you can never show that they have the same group structure.
So the question was, could there be bijections?
Yes, there certainly can be bijections, but they'll never be uh they'll never be isomorphic as groups.
Yeah. Okay.
Okay.
So the formalization of this idea where you have some sort of map and it preserves the group structure, but you don't make any sort of assumption that the thing is bijective.
That's this idea of homomorphism.
So,
the formalization homomorphisms
are maps F between groups such that
f of X * Y is f of X * f of Y.
Okay.
And so can people give me examples of homomorphisms?
Yes, go ahead.
Exactly.
Every isomorphism is a homomorphism.
Suppose I have a pair of groups, g1, g2. Is there necessarily a homomorphism between them?
Does anybody have any ideas?
Yeah, go ahead.
No, because they may not have the same order.
Well, that would be a problem if I were asking is there always an isomorphism between groups, but homomorphisms, we don't know preserve
things like the order of a group.
How about mapping everything to the identity?
Absolutely.
So there's always a trivial homomorphism between any two groups.
trivial homomorphism. So between g1, g2,
and that's defined by just taking f ofx to the identity element of g2.
That certainly preserves the group structure because uh f ofx * Y, well, that's automatically E and that's automatically the same thing as f ofx * f of Y because both of those are E.
Okay.
Another piece of terminology.
images.
So the notion of image is about seeing a group through the lens of a homomorphism.
So suppose I have F going from g1 to g2. So I'll just draw these things as some sort of blobs.
Not everything in g2 is necessarily going to be hit by F.
But some subset of it will be, certainly.
So here's g1, here's g2.
And the shaded in part, the part that's hit by G1 is called the image.
Now this is a familiar notion. This is from linear algebra. There were a couple of different names. You might have called it image. You probably also called it column space of a matrix.
Um in our case, we just call it the image and it's the set of f ofx in g2 as X ranges over g1.
And um the uh main professor, Professor Gross will pick up on this next time.
Um, are there any questions about what we've done so far?
Great. Now I'm going to list the homework exercises.
Think about the fact that the image can be sub.
You can think about that today.
It's it's actually on the problem set.
Okay. It'll be posted online as well, but
So a couple of these you've seen already in in more or less detail in class today, but it's still a very good idea to work through the details of it.
about the fact that the image can be. You can think about that.
It's it's actually it's on the problem set.
Okay.
moment.
It'll be posted online as well, but
So a couple of these you've seen already in in more or less detail in class today, but it's still a very good idea to work through the details of it.
Okay, great.
This is due on Monday.
So Friday assignments are due on Mondays, etc.
Yeah, go ahead.
Will there be solutions posted? Yeah, there there will be
solutions posted to the assignments.
Okay, great.
Yeah.
When are we going to get homework back from Friday? Oh, yeah. So, uh,
the way this is going to work at least for the beginning for the first while is that um you won't necessarily get your
homework back on the next lecture uh after you hand it in, but in general, you'll be getting your homework assignments, accumulated homework assignments back on Wednesdays.
Okay, great.