for this course. We may have others.
He did it last year as a pro at this.
You're a senior this year, Peter?
Okay. He knows everything about it.
Now, I want to explain how the course is going to be given because uh I have too many responsibilities this year
uh beyond just teaching in the math department.
So I have to frequently go out on the road uh and
so at those times Peter Green will substitute for me as a lecturer and in fact, he'll lecture for you on Friday.
So you get an idea of his penetrating and lucid style of presentation before you have to decide whether you want to choose the course.
I would imagine that Peter will be lecturing for me one out of every four or five lectures.
But I don't know exactly when they're going to be now because I don't have my exact schedule.
The way we're going to organize the course
is that the textbook is going to be this nice algebra text by Mike Artin.
So this is quite an advanced algebra text.
I think it can be used profitably by students here and by students at MIT for whom it was written.
Mike Artin is a senior uh guy in the MIT math department, one of the leading algebraists and algebraic geometers of the last 50 years.
When you get further on, you'll learn about his work in the Artin representability theorem and you'll learn about his work with Grothendieck in settling the uh the foundations of of modern algebraic geometry.
In any case, he wrote this book in mind to show really how algebra interacts with a lot of other subjects.
And uh that's really the way it it does later in mathematics and I think it's a great viewpoint here.
I think you'll find it a challenging text.
By the way, Mike's father was Emil Artin, who was the greatest number theorist of the 20th century, invented the subject called class field theory.
So he comes from a distinguished uh distinguished mathematical tradition.
Um I think we're going to do homework assignments every class.
Now I know most of you are coming out. What what is the background one should have for this? Everyone wants to know that.
So, if you've come out of 23 or 25 or 55,
you're fine.
That you you clearly have the background to take this course.
If you've been through 21 and you felt comfortable with the linear algebra in 21B, because I'm going to need some of that.
And you you are willing to move to a slightly more abstract level of knowledge,
this is good.
Otherwise, I would suggest taking a course like a 121 or a 101 to get to that level of abstraction.
But if you're coming out of 23, 25, or 55, it's fine.
I know that those courses had weekly assignments and big long weekly assignments where everyone would devote all of Thursday night or all of Sunday night to finishing the assignment.
I want to do it more on a every every lecture there'll be some assignments to keep people up to date.
And the reason is that unlike 25 or 55 or or 23, taking an algebra course is like learning a new language.
Algebra is really more of a language of modern mathematics.
The way mathematics organizes itself and speaks to itself.
And so when you learn a new language, you have to go to language lab a lot, you have to do a lot of keeping up and practicing.
That's the way I've got it organized now.
Peter is even going to arrange for some assignments due Wednesday and Friday.
Those are optional assignments, right?
Are they available now on the web page?
Not yet.
They will be available on the web page.
Those are optional assignments, highly recommended so you can check whether you understood what I said today, but also to give you an idea of what the level of homework is going to be, so you can assess how much work there's going to be for the course before you decide to take it or not.
And then once we get to Friday, we'll just start doing regular assignments due Monday and Wednesday and Friday.
We'll also organize problem sessions, probably on Tuesday and Thursday once we get our CA situation straightened out and find out how many people are in the course and when they're free.
But we're not going to do that um right now.
There'll be two-hour exams in the course.
Those weeks are marked on the web page. We're going to get a full syllabus up on the web page so you see exactly what date you're going to have the hour exam and there'll be a three-hour final in January.
Questions in general before I start actually talking about the math in the course?
That was easy.
Okay.
So what are we going to use from linear algebra?
Well, if you want to review your linear algebra in a nice way, it's done in chapter one of this book.
And I'm going to go through it and just tell you what we need from it so you can go back and find out what you remember and what you don't remember, etc.
Um, because we need some linear algebra initially to generate examples of groups, which are the first topic of the course.
And the linear algebra we're going to need all concerns the set of all n by n matrices.
where n and n is the same number, so square matrices.
Now, the entries of the matrix, if you're if you're in the ith row and you're in the jth column,
the entry would be Aij.
That that'll be the notation I'll use.
So the first row looks like A11, A12, up to A1n.
And then we have An1 down here all the way over to Ann.
The entries of a matrix are numbers.
That's what Artin says in the beginning. And they can be numbers in various different places.
But before we get into the theory of rings or vector spaces or abstract fields, I'm going to take the entries all just to be real numbers.
And the set of all n by n matrices, I'm going to denote M n R.
So that's all collections of n by n matrices.
So those of you who have studied linear algebra know that that's a vector space over the real numbers, it has dimension n squared because you have you have a basis for that vector space of the matrices that have zeros everywhere but a one in the ith jth place.
So in particular, as a vector space, you can do a number of things in this in this uh set.
For example, you can add matrices,
A + B.
So if you have a matrix where the entries are Aij and you have a matrix where the entries are Bij,
then the sum of these two matrices has entries Aij + Bij.
So you just add the elements in the ijth place.
That's the addition law in the vector space of n by n matrices.
And you can also multiply matrices by a real scalar.
If you have a a real number alpha and you have an n by n matrix Aij,
then you can multiply alpha times A and get the matrix where the entries are alpha times Aij.
Namely, multiply every member by alpha.
That's the scalar multiplication in the vector space.
So that's what makes this a a real vector space of dimension n squared.
As I say, you have to write down a basis, that's not difficult.
Now, what's unusual, that would be true for n by m matrices too.
You can add them, you can multiply them by scalars and the dimension is m times n.
What's unusual about n by n matrices is not just that you can add them or multiply them by scalars, but that you can multiply them.
So that's another thing I'm going to ask you to remember from linear algebra.
Is it okay if I erase this?
Because of the video setup today, which didn't know whether I was going to be using this or the blackboard, I have to stay somewhat on the left side of the board.
With your apologies.
So all that wonderful space, I'm aware of it, but I'm not going to use it.
Okay?
Is this okay the way I am?
Good.
Okay, so that's a a big thing about n by n matrices is that there's a multiplication,
which is a fairly complicated operation. Namely, if you have two matrices A and B, you can define a new matrix A times B.
So, uh those of you who've studied this since uh 10th grade, know that the uh if this has entries Cij,
then you get the ijth entry of Cij in the following manner.
You go across the ith column of A, ith row of A,
you go down the jth column of B,
you multiply this element by this element, then you multiply this element by this element and add those,
you multiply and you add up.
So the formula in mathematics, although it's not that useful, is the sum over K of uh what? Aik times Bkj.
And you might wonder what the heck is that mean, but it certainly defines given two n by n matrices, a third.
The matrix multiplication.
Now, when you study linear algebra right, and we will review linear algebra done right, you get a little bit away, you step back from the theory of matrices and you see what matrices represent.
And what matrices represent are linear operators.
So in particular, this is the set of linear operators from an n-dimensional real vector space to itself.
Every matrix is some a way of writing down a specific linear transformation.
We'll do that later on, but it's good thing to bear in mind.
Because if you understand that a matrix represents a linear transformation, then what multiplication of matrices represents is the composition of transformations.
That's not obvious from this formula at all. You have to you have to unwind a million things to see that.
So if A represents the transformation that of T from Rn to Rn,
and B represents the transmit let's see, I'll do uh B first and A second.
And B represents a transformation S from Rn to Rn,
represented by B, and remind yourself how this works, and that's done in Artin too.
Then the product, first do B, then do A, represents the composition of the transformations, first take the transformation S and compose it with the transformation T.
Now, one thing that we emphasize a lot when you study linear algebra is that that may not be equal to first doing the transformation T and then doing the transformation S.
So remember, and this is really important, that it is true that if you add A to B, it's the same as B to A.
That's just the commutativity of the laws of addition, because matrix addition just takes place coordinate by coordinate.
But
it is not necessarily true that A times B is equal to B times A.
There are examples where this is not equal.
So the only way to really convince you of that is to write down a specific example.
So I will write down a specific example for you, which Artin uses.
If you multiply this matrix, you have to go to 2 by 2 matrices because multiplication of 1 by 1 matrices is just multiplication of real numbers.
Right? I mean if if n is this is k goes from 1 to n.
So if n is equal to 1, this is just you get this matrix by taking the product of the entry in A by the product of the entry in B. And multiplication of real numbers is commutative.
But if you go to 2 by 2 matrices, it's no longer the case.
So for example, if you multiply this matrix by this matrix,
you'll find that the only non-zero entry you get is when you go across this row and down this column, right? So that would be an entry up here.
And all the other entries you find to be zero.
On the other hand, whoops, did I just do that wrong?
Uh yeah, it should be, sorry, the last row, the top row and the yeah.
They're all zero? No.
0, 1.
So if I go across this row and that column, I get a one, but in all the other cases, the one is multiplied by zero and I get zero.
Let's try it in the other direction, see if I got this right. This would be typical where I work this example out wrong.
So that's this matrix here, then this one goes up here.
Are there any places where we get a non-zero entry here?
This is zero, this is zero, this is zero, and this is zero.
So this turns out to be the zero matrix.
So, this is the product of A and B, this is the product of B and A. These matrices are clearly different.
By the way, this matrix I'll just call the zero matrix.
It's the zero element of the vector space.
It's whatever, it's the element of the vector space such that when you add it to an arbitrary vector, you get the vector back.
Because you're not changing anything.
The matrix that looks like this, 1 1 1 1 1 all down the diagonal and zero elsewhere, I'll call that the the identity matrix.
That's a distinguished matrix.
And that has the property, if you work out this addition this multiplication law, that if you multiply anything by the identity matrix, you get it back.
So um, I'm running out of room here, let's go here.
So 0 + A is equal to A + 0 is equal to A. And no matter which side you multiply by the identity matrix, sorry, is I times A,
sorry, this is, yeah, this is A, if you add zero, and if you multiply by I, you get A.
So you have a multiplicative identity and an additive identity.
Okay, some other laws of matrix multiplication uh and addition.
For example, you have the distributive law and you have the associative law.
So the distributive law says if you multiply A times B + C, it's the same as multiplying A by B and then adding the product of A by C.
And the associative law, which is the most important, is that if you multiply A times B times C and you first multiply B times C and then times A, that's the same thing as multiplying A by B and then multiplying by C.
So the normal laws of arithmetic, addition and multiplication, all hold except for the commutativity of multiplication.
Now, you might ask, how do I prove something like this?
Well, it's truly hideous if you try to do it with this formula for the matrix product.
You know, but if you think of it in terms of composition of transformations, these are three different transformations. There's an S, T, and maybe an R.
Mhm, or U, let's call it U for a transformation.
And to do A composed with B and C would be first compose S with U and then compose with T.
And to do this would be first compose U with S, uh sorry, S with T and then compose with U. But all all two ways of doing it are just giving you the composed
transformation where you take U and then you take S and then you take T. Namely, the the effect of this on any given vector in Rn is to calculate T of S of U of V.
No matter which way you do it.
So if you think of it in terms of composition of transformations, this associative law is more or less clear. Same thing you can think of the distributive law if you want to.
Uh, in any case, the way this was proved in the original world of linear algebra before people understood linear algebra uh linear transformations was just by computing with this formula, which as I say, is not the most pleasant thing to do.
Okay.
So these are what I want you to remember about multiplication and addition of n by m matrices.
And as I say, it's all reviewed in chapter one, but I'm not going to go over that. I'm going to assume you've seen this.
Have most of you seen this material?
No.
How many have not seen anything about n by n matrices? I'm just amused.
Don't be embarrassed. I got to know.
Okay.
Now, a much trickier thing about n by n matrices is the question of inversion.
So we say A is invertible, an n by n matrix,
if and only if there exists a matrix B with the property that when you multiply on either side by B, you get to the identity matrix.
So the it requires the existence of a second matrix.
Now, invertibility is a tricky business.
It's a tricky business in matrix theory.
Not every matrix is invertible.
For example, the zero matrix is never invertible because if you multiply any matrix by zero,
you get zero.
If you have zeros in all entries, no matter what the entries of A are, when you compute the matrix product, you get zero.
So there's no way I could find another matrix to multiply by zero to get the identity, because any product with zero is zero.
So, example, zero, I is invertible.
There's a good case.
You take B is equal to I.
And zero is not invertible.
But between those two, it's it's a tricky business.
For example, for 1 by 1 matrices, it's an easy answer, but already for 2 by 2, it's quite complicated.
So for 1 by 1 matrices,
So the matrix just looks like A,
uh is invertible if and only if A is not equal to zero.
And then the inverse matrix is just given by the entry 1 over A.
That's the only thing you could multiply A by and get to the identity matrix, which is just the the the thing one.
So a real number is invertible if and only if it's non-zero.
For 2 by 2 matrices,
it turns out to be is invertible, I'll just give you the answer, if and only if a certain quantity is non-zero,
namely if you take the product of A by D and you subtract off the quantity BC is not equal to zero.
And in fact, if that's the case, I'll write down the inverse matrix for you.
Usually, if you you don't want to just know if a matrix is invertible or not, you want to know what its inverse is. So if this is A,
then A inverse is equal to 1 over AD - BC, and you can write that real number down because this number was non-zero, so it has an inverse,
times the matrix D - B - C A.
And this means you take the scalar product of this matrix by that real number.
So we can check that.
We ought to do at least one matrix multiplication in class to see that I can do it.
So let's multiply the matrix ABCD by the matrix D - B - C and A.
Okay, the entry here.
I go across this row and down this column.
I get AD - BC.
The entry here.
- AB + AB.
So the entry here is zero.
The entry here.
I go across this row and down this column.
CD - CD.
Zero.
And the entry here, I go across this row and here I get - BC + AD, same thing, AD - BC.
So if I just took this matrix, I can multiply by my matrix and get something which isn't the identity, but looks pretty close to the identity.
Namely, it's a scalar multiple of the identity.
And the only problem might be that this scalar might be zero.
But if this scalar is non-zero, then I could have taken this matrix and multiplied by one over it, and I would get the identity.
Okay?
Now, in general, the answer to the question of whether a matrix is invertible or not is the following.
There's a certain function from the set of n by n matrices to the real numbers called the determinant,
which I'll write just det, which maps n by n matrices over the reals to the real numbers.
And the determinant of a matrix is a polynomial in its entries. It's a polynomial of degree n in its entries.
21:45,
So, for example, this is the determinant of the 2 by 2 matrix A.
And you probably know the formula for the determinant of a 3 by 3 matrix or even generally the formula for the determinant of an n by n matrix. It's it's given by a formula, determinant of A is sum over n factorial terms with a plus or minus one in front of it, and then products of of n matrix entries.
So n factorial, here is just two terms, but if you go to a 3 by 3 matrix, there are six terms in the determinant expression. 4 by 4, there are 24 terms. In short, it's a useless formula.
Because once you get to 10 by 10 matrices, you don't want to be dealing with 10 factorial terms.
Nonetheless, there is such a formula.
And the the the key fact is A is invertible if and only if the determinant of A as a real number is not equal to zero,
in which case there's a formula for the the inverse of A.
And the formula looks very much like this formula. The formula then looks like you get, in fact, there's always a matrix, there is an unique matrix, that means there exists a unique matrix B such that AB is equal to BA is equal to the determinant of A times the identity matrix.
There's always such a matrix.
You can't always multiply something to get to the identity, but you can always find a unique matrix where the product is the determinant of A times the identity matrix.
Well, no, I shouldn't say unique. I mean, if A were the zero matrix, then then anything would work. So sorry, there exists a there's a natural matrix. Let me just say that.
And that B is sometimes called the matrix of cofactors, and you get its entries by taking partial determinants around A. Have you all seen that once or twice? So this is this is the matrix, for example, of cofactors of the original 2 by 2 matrix A.
So there's always a matrix you can find where you multiply to get the determinant, and if this is non-zero, you divide B by the determinant and you found a matrix to multiply through to get the identity.
Okay, so now I can make my first important definition in this course.
So this vector space of n by n matrices is not what we're really interested in.
We're interested in a subset that I'm going to call GLN of R,
which is a subset of all n by n matrices over R.
And this subset consists of all matrices A such that the determinant of A is not equal to zero.
Or equivalently, A such that there is an inverse
matrix A inverse.
So for 1 by 1 matrices, the the set is everything but the zero matrix.
But for 2 by 2 matrices, you have to throw away other matrices.
For example, you have to throw away that matrix that we wrote down before like this.
This is not in GL2 because its determinant is 0 * 0 - 1 * 0, which is 0.
So this is a large set of n by n matrices.
It's defined by the non-vanishing of a certain polynomial on this set.
So almost everything's in it, but we just want to look at that set of matrices, the invertible ones.
By the way, if an inverse exists, it's unique.
Let's write that, let's prove that for ourselves.
This again is all in Artin's chapter one.
Exists, it is unique. So one can talk about the inverse of a matrix.
There can't be two different matrices that serve as an inverse for a matrix.
And the reason is the following. Suppose we had two inverses.
So suppose I could say AB is equal to AC
and it's also equal to I.
Suppose that were the case.
And I want to show B is equal to C.
Well, remember that what an inverse is defined to be is not just a right inverse under multiplication, but a left inverse under multiplication.
So if I took this thing and I multiplied on the left by any matrix that inverts A, for example, B,
I could say, well, this implies that BAB
is equal to BAC.
And then I use the associative law to reassociate things.
This on the other hand is BA times B,
and this is BA times C.
And since B was assumed to be an inverse for A,
this is equal to the identity times B, and this is equal to the identity times C.
And the identity times any matrix is itself, and therefore B has to equal C.
So even though this matrix here doesn't have to be unique, as I said, if A were the zero matrix, any matrix B would work here.
However, if you use the canonical one, the matrix of cofactors, and the determinant turns out to be non-zero so that you can divide by it, then that inverse is in fact unique.
And so I should add that. There is an inverse matrix A inverse
which is unique.
All right, now let's look at the properties of this subset of uh
the n by n matrices, because we gain things and we lose things.
One thing that we lose right away
is addition.
There is no addition defined on the set GLNR.
If you
I mean, you even know that for one by one matrices,
you could take a the matrix one and you could add it to the matrix minus one and both of those are invertible
and their sum is the matrix zero which isn't invertible.
So there's no addition law.
So we lose the vector space,
plus
or
scalar multiplication by zero.
If you took a nice invertible matrix and you multiplied it by the zero scalar,
you'd get down to zero which is not invertible.
So forget about addition.
However,
the beautiful thing is that it's closed under multiplication.
So I'll give you two proofs of that.
Yeah,
Peter,
did you have a question?
You're just stretching.
Anyone else need to stretch?
Here's
here's a principle I like to do in my lectures.
So, uh since it's a principle, um it'll apply.
Um I go pretty fast
and when nobody's stopping me, my tendency is to go faster.
So, if you find yourself getting a minute behind, and then two minutes behind, and then three minutes behind in your notes,
it's not a profitable experience
because all you're doing is writing down gibberish which you're going to have to decipher later on.
Much better that you're with me when I'm talking about it.
So, the principle is that anyone can ask
for a minute or two of silence.
This may may not be repeated 30 times in the course of a lecture.
But if you feel
that you need two minutes to just catch up to what I've said on the board and digest it so that you can even ask me a meaningful question,
you may just raise your hand and ask for some silence.
Believe me,
the other people in the class will appreciate it.
And if you're confused,
undoubtedly someone else is confused.
So I've said something either too fast
or incorrect.
And I will make mistakes. That's why Peter's here.
But he may miss it too.
Okay.
It's closed under multiplication.
I'll give you two proofs.
Here's the first proof.
Suppose
A and B are invertible.
I have to prove
that the product
A times B
is invertible.
Well,
to
to prove something's invertible,
I just have to find
an inverse for it.
Can someone suggest
what would be a nice
left inverse for it?
Go ahead.
Yes.
B to the minus one.
Yeah,
B - 1 A inverse exists.
So call this
consider
this product.
And
let's multiply
it on the left
times AB.
So I have
B inverse
A inverse.
This is the way it's associated,
times
AB.
Now
once you have
the associative
law for three
for three
products,
you can reassociate
for any number of products.
That's
a nice fact
of about the associative
law. So this
can be written
as B inverse
times A inverse A times B.
Which
is B inverse
times the identity matrix
times B.
Because
A A inverse,
A was invertible,
so there's an identity
matrix.
And then
the identity
commutes with
any matrix
and so this B inverse I
is I B inverse,
so this is I
times B inverse B.
And then
I associate
these two together
to get I times I
which
is the identity.
So namely,
this is the inverse.
Notice
that I have to take
them in the opposite
order. The inverse
is not
A inverse
times B inverse,
but B
and then
similarly,
if you multiply
on the right
by this,
first you multiply
the B times B inverse,
that cancels,
then you multiply
the A times A inverse.
So that's the first proof.
Suppose
we took this
definition
of invertible.
So we'd have to say
that if we had
two matrices,
each of which
had a non-zero
determinant,
their product
had a non-zero
determinant.
That's what we're saying,
right?
If that previous
condition
for invertibility
really worked,
just being a non-zero
determinant.
How would we check
that? That if
two matrices
had a non-zero
determinant,
their product
had a non-zero
determinant.
Someone else?
Yeah.
We know
from algebra
that
that A times
that B is
that AB.
Exactly.
So
if you
another
this is the first
proof,
and the second
proof is there's a famous
identity
for determinants
that the determinant
of a product
of two matrices
is the product
of the determinants.
Again,
you can never prove
that using
the definition
of determinant
as the sum of n factorial
terms,
but we'll see how to prove
that intelligently
in a while.
Now,
if you know
this,
and each of these
numbers
are non-zero,
the product of
two non-zero
real numbers
is a non-zero
real number.
So
then for
this set
is closed
under multiplication.
Exactly.
What can we say
about the multiplication
on this set?
Well,
it has the following
properties.
Can I erase
this now, guys?
Normally I'll be using
more board. We'll
be set up
a little bit better
next time.
It's closed
under multiplication.
Has
a multiplicative
identity
which is the matrix
I.
I times
anything
is the
something
times I
is itself.
Uh
has
multiplicative
inverses.
A inverse,
because
that's how the set
was defined.
It's exactly
the set of matrices
that have a multiplicative
inverse.
So anything
in this set,
you can take
products.
There's a multiplicative
identity
on the set.
Anything
has an inverse.
And finally,
the product
is associative.
Because
that was true
of the product
on the larger set
of matrices.
AB
times C
is A
times
BC.
So,
we have four
properties
of this
subset
of the set
of matrices.
It has
a multiplication
law. The multiplication
law is associative.
There's
an identity
element,
and there's an inverse
for every element.
And
those properties
make up
the properties
of what we call
a group.
So
this
is the first
and most important
example
of a group.
So I'll now tell you
what a group is.
And that's why we need
the linear algebra
to generate
for us
immediately
some good examples
of groups.
I'll give you some more
examples,
but that's our first
example.
So
a group
G
is a set
with
a product
operation.
So
if you have two elements
in the set,
you can take
their product,
not necessarily
commutative.
So g
times
h
which is
one
associative,
two
has an identity
element
which is sometimes
denoted
E
or sometimes
denoted
one,
has
inverses,
namely every
element
in the group,
there's
another
element
called g
inverse
whose product
with g
is the identity
element.
That's it.
Those are the properties
of a group.
A product,
it has to be associative,
there has to be
an distinguished
identity
element
there,
and there have to be
inverses
for every element.
It does
not have to be
commutative.
If
if
GH
is equal
to HG
for all
pairs,
you either
say the group
say
G
is commutative
or sometimes
abelian.
Abelian
comes
from the great
Norwegian
mathematician
Abel,
who was one of
the invent
Niels Abel,
early 19th century
Norwegian
mathematician,
who uh
was one of the
originators
of group theory.
The great originator
of group theory
was the famous
young
French
mathematician
Evariste
Galois.
Both
Abel
and Galois
lived in the early
decades
of the 19th century,
both died
in their 20s.
Galois
died
as a result
of a duel.
Abel
died
basically
because he was
too poor
and couldn't find
employment
for a Norwegian,
it was very hard
to find employment
in mathematical
Europe
at the time.
But together
they really
put together
the foundations
of group theory.
Galois's
work wasn't
appreciated
for about
50 years.
So he
sent his work
to the great
mathematicians
of the time,
Gauss,
Koshi,
etc.,
and they
all put it
aside.
It was only
at the end of
the 19th century
when French
mathematician
Jordan
realized
how fundamental
Galois's
discoveries
were,
many of which
were written
up in a letter
he sent to a friend
the night
before he died
in this duel.
If any of
you have been
to Paris
and take
the Ligne de Sceaux,
uh
you pass
through a beautiful
or I shouldn't say
beautiful,
a disgusting
Parisian
suburb
called
Bourg-la-Reine
where
Galois's
father
was mayor
and Galois
born
was born
and lived
much of his life.
And
there's a plaque
in the most
disgusting
uh
intersection
in the middle of
Bourg-la-Reine
where the trucks
are going
by
and it says,
"Ici
est né
Evariste
Galois,
illustre
mathématicien
français."
That's
the way a country
honors its heroes.
Um,
actually
many streets
in Paris
are named
after mathematicians.
If any of
you have been
on the rue
Monge,
Monge
was a great
mathematician
who accompanied
Napoleon
to Egypt
to do surveying
and Egyptology.
But
um,
Galois
is undoubtedly
the most famous
young
mathematician
to die young.
But
in his
head,
he discovered
not only
the theory
of finite fields,
which
we'll cover
later on,
and wrote
the treatment
of finite fields,
it's the best
treatment
in the literature
today,
but
also
discovered
almost
all the foundations
of group theory.
And
it was Galois
who realized
there could be
very interesting
groups
where GH
was not equal
to HG.
Yeah.
Is
it required
that the product
operation
is closed,
is that assumed?
Yeah,
when I say
a product
operation,
it means
that for any two
elements
in the set
G,
there's
a product
GH
which is in
G.
So,
associated
to any two
elements,
you get a third.
I'm going to get
Now this
this is a very interesting
group,
the
the group of
invertible
matrices,
in that
already
when we get
to 2 by 2
matrices,
we have a lot
of non-commutative
groups.
Right?
You can find
two invertible
matrices.
The ones
I wrote down
by the way
weren't invertible.
So
that'll be
a challenge
for you
to find
invertible
matrices
such that
AB
is not equal
to BA.
Good
homework problem
there,
Peter.
It's
already there?
The home
it's
he's ahead of me.
Damn
kids.
Um,
anyhow,
uh
so,
uh,
but good
question.
Yeah,
that
you must
have you
you have to stay
in your set.
For any two
elements
in the set,
sorry,
the
product
is defined
and in the set,
it's
associative,
G
H
K
is the same
as G
H
times K.
There's
an identity
element
E
such that
G
is equal
to G
E
is equal
to G
for every
element
in the set.
I
let me give you
a simpler
example
of a group
because
this seems
awfully
complicated
uh
to go through
to get a group.
So
you've been doing
groups
all your lives.
Um
it's like
speaking
prose.
So
here's an example
of a group.
An abelian
group.
Why don't we do
an abelian group?
The
simplest
abelian
group is
the integers.
So
that's the
you know,
plus or minus
1,
2,
plus or minus
3,
positive
and negative
integers
denoted
by a bold
face Z
here.
So,
uh
the
uh product
operation
in the integers
is addition.
You know,
A + B.
That's
the product
operation.
Uh
that's
clearly
associative.
When you add
three things,
it doesn't make
any difference
which order
you do the adding.
What's
the identity
element
for addition
in the group
Z?
This
kind of stupid.
Zero.
Exactly.
The
identity
element
is zero.
If you add
0 to A,
you always
get A.
What's
the inverse
element?
What is A
inverse?
minus
A. So if you take
the negative
number, that's
how that's
why we have negative
numbers
really, to turn
counting
numbers
into a group.
If you think
of it.
Well,
what is
-3?
It's the
thing you
add to three
to get zero.
Okay?
And
um
well,
that does
it.
So
this is a very
simple
group
which has the
property
that A + B
is B + A.
So groups
like this,
of course,
were studied
before there
was a notion
of a group.
I
I'll tell you
a funny story.
So
a a great
um
great German
mathematician
who I've
collaborated
with many
times
and
is an altogether
um
is
is a rare
example
of a prodigy
who actually
worked
out,
uh
his name is
Don
Zagier.
Uh
he's the director
of the Max
Planck Institute
uh for
mathematical
research
in in
Bonn. And
um
Don
went to
uh
schools
in about
seven
different
countries
when he was
young.
By the age
of 13,
he was speaking
nine
different
languages
and
applied
to get
his
uh
undergraduate
degree
at Oxford.
And
he had taken
the A-levels
and O-levels
even though
he'd never
been to England,
and
uh
he was denied
admission
on the grounds
that no one
could attend
Oxford
before the
age of 16.
So,
he got into
MIT
and finished
in two years,
and then applied
to Oxford
as a graduate
student
at 15,
and there was no
objection
at that point
because
that was as
a graduate student.
So
Don
said
when he recalled
his algebra
course
from MIT,
he
was so
confused
the whole time
he took the course,
but he learned
how to do it
because
he's a very
good mathematician.
He
said that
his idea
of a group
as he got out
of this course
was that a group
was the integers.
All
groups
were the integers.
Except
that somehow
when you were doing
the problems,
you weren't
allowed
to use the
fact that
A + B
was B + A.
And he
thought
that this was
very strange,
and
it was a strange
way to teach,
but if
those were the
rules of higher
mathematics,
he would go
with it.
So,
I want to point
out that sometimes
you are allowed
to use the rules
that A + B
is B + A
when it holds.
Another
example
of a group is
any vector
space.
That's
a group because
you just forget
about the scalar
multiplication.
The addition,
the
the binary
operation
is addition
of vectors.
The
identity
element
is the zero
vector.
Right?
You add the
zero vector
and any vector,
you get the vector
back.
The
the
the inverse
element
is the negative
vector.
Okay,
so
you just
you just forget
scalar
multiplication.
So
it turns
out that once
you come up
with this rather
simple definition,
there are groups
all over
the place.
This is
also an abelian
group.
In
some sense,
the most
general
group you
get is
as follows.
Uh
and
this will be
the last thing
I'll talk about
and then I'll
let you get out
of here.
Uh
if you
start
with any set,
call
it the set
T.
And
you let
G
be the set
of all
bijections
G
from T
to itself.
So
that means
one to one
and onto
maps
from a set
to itself.
All
bijections.
Then
that's a group,
it's sometimes
I'll denote
it by the symmetries
of T.
Or
the symmetric
group of the set
T.
is a group.
Someone's
got a phone call.
I
hope it's not me.
Mine plays
La Traviata.
So
occasionally
there'll be an emergency,
someone's
about to jump
off a bridge
or something
that requires
the attention
of the Dean.
So
you'll hear
I figure
I
I wanted
a cheerful
tune.
So
to deal with it.
So this is
a group
under composition.
Composition
of
bijections.
If you
compose
one bijection
with another,
you get a third
because if two
maps are one
to one and you compose
them, you get
a third one
to one map.
If two maps
are onto
and you compose
them you get another
onto
map.
So that's
the
the composition
law
of transformations.
The
identity
element
is the
identity
transformation
that takes
every element
in the set
T to itself.
That's
certainly
one to one and
onto.
The
inverse element
is the inverse
transformation.
If you have a
transformation
that's one to one and
onto,
you can send
the transformation
back.
That's G
inverse.
And
composition
of maps
is associative,
just like
we prove
composition
of linear
maps
is associative.
Because
if you have three
maps,
then
and you compose
them, no matter
how which
way you do it,
then it's
the final
map that
takes
an element
in T
first to this
map, then
to that map,
then to a third
thing in T.
So
this is
the most
general
group in
some sense
of the word.
One second,
I just want to
finish.
And
all groups,
we'll
see somehow
arise
by putting
extra
conditions
on this
invertible
bijection.
So for
example,
this group
GLNR,
how did
that come about?
Well,
I started
out with a
set
which was
Rn,
the
set which
was Rn.
And
I considered
all invertible
maps
from Rn
to Rn
which
preserve
the linearity.
Which
preserve
the structure
of a vector
space. That's
not all
maps, but
the ones that
preserve
some structure.
And
that's how I got
invertible
matrices.
So
we're going to
see that
this is
somehow,
and this was
Galois's
big idea
that when
you study
maps or
symmetries
of a set,
that was
one group
and then you could
get very interesting
groups by
studying
symmetries
that preserve
some extra
structure
in the set,
like some
linear
structure
on the set.
And
in particular,
we're going to have
one very
famous
group
where this
T
is the set
of
an
a finite
set
and all finite
sets
are determined
by the number
of elements
in them.
So the set
from 1
to n,
then
we'll call the
symmetry
group of T,
the
symmetric
group S
sub n.
We'll
just write
it that way.
And
what is
this turns
out to be
a group with
only
finitely
many elements
in it
because
there are only
finitely
many ways
you can permute
n different
objects.
How many
ways are there
permuting
n different
objects?
N factorial.
Yeah,
so this is
a group
where
it's a finite
group
of
order
N
factorial
and you'll find
that it's non-abelian
and you should
check that
once
n
is at least
three.
So
once
there's a finite
group with
six elements
in it,
that's
non-abelian.
The
permutations,
the
one to one
maps
of a set
of three
things to
itself.
And
you should play
with that
a little bit.
Okay,
this is
our introduction.
This gives
you an idea
of what groups
are.
Peter
has some
interesting
things. Are
you want to put
them on the board?
Why not?
So
here's the homework.
Recommended,
optional.
And
it'll be
on the web
page for
those of you
who have to run
now, but
I'll put it on the
blackboard
too.
This will give
you an idea
of whether
you're up
to speed,
whether this
is the right
course for
you.
And if you want to
talk to me
or Peter
about it,
please do.
So
read
1.1
and
pages
to 42
and
the exercises
1.1.7
1.1.16
and
1.1.17.
Do
those three
exercises.
If you want to
hand it
in,
Peter
or Peter will
take a look
at them for
you.
Okay?
Thanks Peter.
See
you guys
on Wednesday.
I think
it was good.